Finding Aid for College of Literature, Science and the Arts (University of Michigan) records, 1846-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
College of Literature, Science and the Arts (University of Michigan) records 1846-2014
University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.
Bimu C22 2 8779
Founded in 1841, the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) is the liberal arts college of the University of Michigan, encompassing over 100 academic departments and non-departmental centers, programs, institutes, museums, and laboratories. The record group includes correspondence, meeting minutes, memoranda, reports, proposals, subject files, and program materials from the administrative offices of the dean and the academic units that make up the college.
518 linear feet
3 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 1665 ) has been received in various installments since 1942.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The College of Literature, Science and the Arts records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The College of Literature, Science and the Arts record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 266-271, 277-282, 285-288, 292-295
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 304, 355, 386, 491
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 366-378, 387-490, 492-518
The College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) commenced classes at the University of Michigan in 1841 as the Department of LS&A. The faculty consisted of two professors, the Reverend George P. Williams, and the Reverend Joseph Whiting. Together they offered study in rhetoric, grammar, Latin and Greek literature and antiquities, algebra, geometry, surveying, natural science, ancient history, and Greek philosophy. Enrollment was seven; a decade later it stood at 57 and the faculty at six.
University President Henry Tappan (1852-1863) endeavored to create a university based on the Prussian model, with the sciences and humanities combined in one school. Innovations undertaken by Tappan included introducing a bachelor of science degree as an alternative to the traditional bachelor of arts degree and providing the opportunity for students to elect courses during their senior year. Professorships in zoology, moral and intellectual philosophy, chemistry and logic, rhetoric, and history were added in the 1850s.
The 1860s continued to see a rise in enrollment. In 1870 women enrolled in the University of Michigan for the first time. By June of 1871, 14 women had entered LS&A. President James B. Angell, who served as president from 1871 to 1909, continued to refine the curriculum based on the Prussian model as originally introduced by Tappan. By the 1878/79 academic year, LS&A seniors could elect half their courses. In addition Angell introduced graduation requirements based on credits: 24 courses were required to earn a bachelor of arts, and 26 were required to earn a bachelor of philosophy, bachelor of science, or a bachelor of letters. The bachelor of letters degree was introduced in 1878.
Graduate work was introduced in LS&A by President Tappan, under the title "university courses." Students were able to receive a masters degree or doctorate by engaging in two or three years of post graduate work and completing exams. In 1912 the graduate school at the University of Michigan was created as an administrative unit separate from LS&A.
An education curriculum was added to LS&A in 1879, when a chair in the science and art of teaching was established. Speech and oratory were introduced to the curriculum in 1884 and LS&A established the first department of speech in the United States in 1892.
From 1841 to 1874 the LS&A faculty elected a president to oversee the department. Henry S. Frieze was elected the first dean of LS&A in 1875, a post in which he served until 1889, excluding the two years he spent as acting president of the university. Martin L. D'Ooge was the first officially appointed dean of LS&A; he was elected by the faculty and his appointment was also approved by the Regents. In the very early years of the school, administrative functions were handled by the university president's office. Even after the official appointment of D'Ooge, the dean was, in effect, an assistant to the president in matters pertaining to LS&A, and mostly concentrated on admissions.
Richard Hudson succeeded D'Ooge as dean in 1897. Hudson was the first dean appointed by the Board of Regents without requiring faculty approval. As LS&A grew, President Angell gave up his active participation in its affairs, retaining only his position as presiding officer at faculty meetings. When John O. Reed became dean in 1907 the administration of LS&A rested completely with the dean. By 1921, an assistant dean was appointed to help in administrative functions.
Graduation requirements were modified in 1912. These new requirements, like those of the 1878/79 academic year, pointed the way toward the present college curriculum. Students were required to take 12 credits in three different academic groupings (later known as distribution requirements) for a complete undergraduate education. For the first time, 120 credit hours were required to graduate and letter grades were established.
The Department of LS&A became the College of LS&A on January 1, 1916. In the twentieth century, many departments that originated in the College of LS&A became autonomous schools, including the School of Forestry in 1902, the School of Business Administration in 1924, and the School of Education in 1921. In 1923, the Department of Geology divided into the Geology and Geography Departments. In 1924/25, a Department of Library Science was added. A Department of Anthropology was initiated in 1928. One year later the Department of Philosophy separated into two departments, Philosophy and Psychology. The Department of Economics and Sociology also divided, and a Department of Journalism was added. Honors courses were first introduced in 1925 providing qualified students with concentrated study in English and history.
Significant changes in LS&A occurred during 1931 with the introduction of a program of concentrated study. The first two years of study were to focus on a liberal arts education, while the last two years were to be spent in concentrated study for the specific degree program chosen. These changes resulted in a need for academic counseling, given the continued expansion in courses and fields of study. Under the administration of the dean, the college created counseling services for underclassmen and departments took on counseling of students in their upperclass specialization.
Upon the death of Dean John R. Effinger in 1933, who had served since 1912, the administration of LS&A was restructured. A temporary executive committee of five faculty members was appointed to perform administrative functions. In September 1933 the regents approved a college reorganization which allowed for the dean to be assisted by an executive committee of six members appointed by the president from a panel selected by the LS&A faculty. The executive committee was charged with investigating and formulating educational and instructional policies for consideration by the faculty and acting for the college in matters of budget, promotion, and appointment.
During Dean Edward Kraus' tenure (1933-1945) a system of faculty evaluations proposed by the local chapter of the American Association of University Professors was adopted. The evaluations included an annual record of each faculty member's publications, student comments on the professor's teaching, and a report on each individual faculty member's professional competence by departmental committees.
In 1940 LS&A boasted 4,895 students and over 300 faculty members, a far cry from the original seven students and two instructors of a century earlier. LS&A also taught 60% of the total educational load at the University of Michigan in 1940.
With the appointment of Dean Hayward Keniston in 1945, an attempt was made to improve faculty morale, to continue to maintain an outstanding faculty, and to create higher standards for both teaching and research. An increase in faculty salaries of 20% to 25% was approved by the regents. Other matters of concern to LS&A administrators were obtaining more research space and better equipment. Dean Keniston also undertook the job of accommodating the returning veterans from World War II. A committee examined curriculum revisions to meet the needs of the more mature students and consulted with experts and other academic institutions to help in planning for their enrollment. Recommendations included reorganizing the art and archaeology departments, combining the Greek and Latin departments into a classics department, and developing five year plans for each department. Administratively, two associate deans were appointed to handle problems of counseling, curriculum, and personnel.
In 1948 the faculty adopted guidelines on evaluation for promotion. The three criteria adopted were teaching, scholarship, and service, especially student counseling. 1949 saw greater cooperation between departments to encourage interdisciplinary work. Department loyalty had sometimes mitigated against the success of some of the innovative interdisciplinary programs introduced after the war, including great books, linguistics, and several five year plans of study such as chemistry and civil engineering. Departments were also opened up administratively with the elimination of department heads and the introduction of chairmen, who were appointed for specified terms.
During Dean Odegaard's tenure (1952-1958), enrollment increased by 34% as LS&A generated 53% of the credit hours on the Ann Arbor campus. Research was fostered by integrating museums and the Institute for Social Research into the college departments that best suited their disciplines. The undergraduate library was also established, enhancing the undergraduate learning experience.
In 1964 a long range planning committee was formed to study the future of the college. LS&A continued to grow faster than the university at large. In 1965 a computer and communications science department was established. In 1968 the Department of Statistics was created and the Department of Library Science became a professional school separate from LS&A.
In the 1970s many new educational concepts were introduced to meet student demands to control their own education. The Residential College (RC), originally established in 1967, took on a larger role in LS&A. The RC is a four-year degree-granting college within the College of LS&A, devoted exclusively to undergraduate education. It was conceived as a small college with enrollment not to exceed 1,200 students to help combat the impersonality of a college as large as LS&A. The original concept called for educational innovation and interdisciplinary studies to be taught in a mixture of small seminars, large lectures, independent study, and frequent meetings with faculty.
Another innovation was the creation of a bachelor of general studies program in which students could tailor their own educational program. Undergraduate education was also enhanced by the introduction of the Course Mart curriculum, designed to overcome the rigidity of the traditional departmental curriculum by creating courses not available elsewhere in the university. Other innovations included peer counseling, more interdisciplinary courses, and mini courses offered for one credit. While some of these innovations continue to be active, Course Mart and mini-courses have slowly lost the interest of students over the years. Much of the decline in interest was attributed to greater flexibility within academic departments to offer different courses and to an increase in interdisciplinary studies. New interdisciplinary programs created included the Women's Studies Program (1973), the Program in Film and Video Studies (1975), and the American Institutes Program (1983), which later became the Program in American Culture.
Throughout the 1970s and 1980s an emphasis was placed on recruitment and retention of minority students and faculty. Minority enrollment stood at ten percent in 1971, an increase over previous years. One program to increase minority enrollments was the Opportunity Program, organized in 1963 to provide scholarships and support services for disadvantaged students. The Center for Afro-American and African studies was established in 1970, in response to student demands.
Two issues of concern to LS&A administration in the 1970s were increasing class size caused by budget constraints and the increasing use of graduate student teaching assistants. At times up to 40% of underclass instruction was provided by teaching assistants. Freshman seminars, small courses taught by faculty members, were introduced in 1976. Unfortunately they were unable to reach a majority of new students.
A major area of concern to faculty within LS&A is the tension between research and teaching. Incentives have been added to improve the quality of teaching, such as university wide teaching awards.
From the mid 1970s and into the 1980s the college faced budget difficulties. At times freezes were put on faculty hiring, and both long term and short term planning became critical in order to prioritize allocation of available resources. A main concern for the LS&A administration was keeping pace with faculty salaries at peer institutions in order to retain and strengthen the faculty. Due to resource reallocation the Department of Geography was discontinued in 1980/81. An LS&A Office of College Development was established to coordinate fundraising in 1978. Also, a greater emphasis was placed on obtaining funds through research grants. Between 1979/80 and 1983/84, sponsored research in the social and natural sciences increased 56%.
Undergraduate education in LS&A underwent a transformation in the early 1990s. The Undergraduate Initiative was developed and designed with the goal of improving and advancing the quality of the undergraduate experience. Class sizes were reduced, residential learning communities were developed, and introductory courses were revamped. New initiatives included Theme Semesters, which brought together faculty and students from a variety of disciplines around a significant topic, and the Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program (UROP), which enabled students to work with professors on original research projects.
The residential learning communities became known as Michigan Learning Communities. The first ones established were the Pilot Program and the Residential College in the 1960's. However, during the 1990's additional Living-Learning Communities were developed to foster learning in the context of smaller communities within a growing university. Some of the programs included the Invention and Creativity Program in Bursley Hall, the 21st Century Program at Mary Markley Hall, the Society and Health Program in Couzens Hall, the Lloyd hall Scholars Program in Alice Lloyd Hall. Also included among the programs are the Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program (UROP), Science and Mathematics, Women in Science and Engineering (WISE), Gender and Leadership, Democracy and Diversity, Residential College, and the Honors Program at Mosher-Jordan Hall, Barbour-Newberry, Stockwell Hall, South and East Quadrangle.
In the year 2001, the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, one of the largest liberal arts colleges in the United States, was comprised of more than 104 academic programs and six museums.
Deans of the Faculty of LS&A
1875-1880 Henry Frieze
1880-1881 Charles K. Adams
1881-1882 Edward Olney
1882-1889 Henry Frieze
Deans of the Department of LS&A
1890-1897 Martin D’Ooge
1897-1907 Richard Hudson
1907-1914 John O. Reed
1912-1915 John R. Effinger (acting)
Deans of the College of LS&A
1915-1933 John R. Effinger
1933-1945 Edward H. Kraus
1945-1951 Hayward Keniston
1951-1952 Burton D. Thuma (acting)
1952-1958 Charles E. Odegaard
1958-1962 Roger W. Heyns
1962-1963 Burton D. Thuma (acting)
1963-1968 William Haber
1968-1970 William L. Hays
1970-1971 Alfred S. Sussman (acting)
1971-1974 Frank H.T. Rhodes
1974-1976 B.E. Frye (acting)
1976-1980 B.E. Frye
1980-1981 John R. Knott (acting)
1981-1989 Peter O. Steiner
1989-1998 Edie Goldenberg
1998-1999 Patricia Gurin (acting)
1999-2002 Shirley Neuman
2002--2003 Terrence J. McDonald (acting)
2003-2013 Terrence J. McDonald
Summary Contents List
DEAN'S FILES
1916-1932 -- Boxes 1-33
1933-1936 -- Boxes 40-42
1936-1937 -- Boxes 43-44
1937-1940 -- Boxes 44-51
1940-1942 -- Boxes 51-57
1942-1943 -- Boxes 57-60
1943-1944 -- Boxes 60-63
1944-1945 -- Boxes 67-69
1945-1946 -- Boxes 70-73
1946-1947 -- Boxes 73-77
1947-1948 -- Boxes 77-79
1948-1949 -- Boxes 80-82
1949-1950 -- Boxes 82-85
1950-1951 -- Boxes 86-89
1951-1952 -- Boxes 89-91
1952-1953 -- Boxes 91-95
1953-1954 -- Boxes 95-99
1954-1955 -- Boxes 99-103
1955-1956 -- Boxes 103-108
1956-1957 -- Boxes 108-113
1957-1958 -- Boxes 113-118
1958-1959 -- Boxes 118-122
1959-1960 -- Boxes 123-128
1960-1961 -- Boxes 128-133
1961-1962 -- Boxes 133-137
1962-1963 -- Boxes 137-141
1963-1964 -- Boxes 141-145
1964-1965 -- Boxes 145-150
1965-1966 -- Boxes 150-156
1966-1967 -- Boxes 156-162
1967-1968 -- Boxes 162-169
1968-1969 -- Boxes 169-175
1969-1970 -- Boxes 175-181
1970-1971 -- Boxes 181-186
Miscellaneous multiple year files (1971 and before) -- Boxes 187-199
1971-1972 -- Boxes 210-215
1972-1973 -- Boxes 216-227
1973-1974 -- Boxes 227-237
1974-1975 -- Boxes 237-248
1975-1976 -- Boxes 248-260
1976-1977 -- Boxes 260-271
1977-1978 -- Boxes 271-282
1978-1979 -- Boxes 282-288
1979-1980 -- Boxes 288-295
Miscellaneous multiple year files (1970s) -- Box 303
1980-1981 -- Boxes 305-311
1981-1982 -- Boxes 312-317
1982-1983 -- Boxes 327-330
1983-1984 -- Boxes 330-333
1984-1985 -- Boxes 336-339
1985-1986 -- Boxes 339-342
1986-1987 -- Boxes 342-347
1987-1988 -- Boxes 356-357
1988-1990 -- Boxes 357-366
1992-1993 -- Boxes 402-404
1993-1994 -- Boxes 404-406
1994-1995 -- Boxes 406-409
1995-1996 -- Boxes 409-412
1996-1997 -- Boxes 412-414
1997-1998 -- Boxes 414-417
1998-1999 -- Boxes 417-419
1999-2000 -- Boxes 420-428
2000-2001 -- Boxes 428-436
2001-2002 -- Boxes 436-444
Multiple year files, 1989-1998 -- Boxes 366-375
1997-1999 -- Boxes 389-400
1973-2002 -- Boxes 444-448
2002-2003 -- Boxes 475-483
2003-2004 -- Boxes 483-490
2004-2005 -- Boxes 492-498
2005-2006 -- Boxes 498-503
2006-2007 -- Boxes 504-509
2007-2008 -- Boxes 509-518
ADMINISTRATIVE FILES
1936-1989 -- Boxes 348-354
1942-1997 -- Boxes 375-378
ASSISTANT AND ASSOCIATE DEANS
Assistant to Dean, L.S. Woodburne, files, 1936-1937 -- Box 200
Associate Dean for Research and Facilities, 1983-1991 -- Boxes 378-380
Associate Dean for Undergraduate Education, 1954-2011 -- Boxes 452- 473 and 516-518
DEPARTMENTAL EVALUATING COMMITTEE
1949 -- Box 334
DEVELOPMENT
Development Fund Scrapbooks -- Boxes 515-516
EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE
Minutes, 1933-1993 -- Boxes 296-303
Agenda books, 1960-1963 -- Boxes 194-195
Minutes, 1993-1999 -- Box 387
Minutes, 1999-2007 -- Boxes 449 to 451
FACULTY MEETINGS
Minutes, 1846-1993 -- Boxes 204-209 and oversize volumes
Minutes, 1993-2007 -- Box 388
REPORTS AND REVIEWS
1972-1996 -- Boxes 381-387
1973-1991 -- Boxes 445-446
SENIOR STAFF MEETINGS
1990-1999 -- Box 388
ARCHIVED WEBSITE
2002, 2003, on CD -- Box CD-2
2010-, online
The records of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) of the University of Michigan date from 1846 with the first meeting of the literary college's faculty. They now span more than a century and a half and comprise over 500 linear feet of minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and subject files detailing the activities of the college from its early beginnings in the mid-nineteenth century to its present status as the largest of the university's colleges. The records are organized into five major series: Dean's Files, 1911-1998; Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1846-1994; Executive Committee 1993-1999; Administrative Files, 1936-1989; and Reports and Reviews.
Dean's files typically include budgetary materials, policy statements, administrative reports, and topical files. From approximately 1957, the dean's records include a separate subseries of departmental files, documenting the increasing complexity of the college's relationship with various LS&A departments, museums, centers, and programs. In addition to Dean's files, the records in later years include an Administrative series, which holds agendas and minutes of executive, curriculum, and faculty meetings; a Reports and Reviews series which is comprised of internal and external evaluation documentation; and records from the office of the Associate Dean for Research and Facilities, which include planning for space and equipment needs during a period of rapid growth in the use of computer technology for teaching and learning.
The administrative records of the college have come to the library in six major accessions beginning in 1942 with small periodic accessions thereafter. In addition, the college has periodically deposited bound record copies of the minute books of the meetings of the LS&A faculty. Covering the years 1846 to the late 1990s, the minute books (oversize volumes, boxes 204 to 209, and box 388) are the most important source of information about the college, especially for the period before World War I when there are few other extant records to document the activities of the university's liberal arts college.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Administration.; Frye, B. E. (Billy Eugene); Rhodes, Frank Harold Trevor.; Steiner, Peter Otto, 1922-; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; Universities and colleges--Departments--Evaluations.
Contributors:
Effinger, John Robert, 1869-1933.; Haber, William, 1899-1988.; Hays, William L. (William Lee), 1926-1995; Heyns, Roger W. (Roger William), 1918-1995; Keniston, Hayward, b. 1883.; Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-1973; Odegaard, Charles E.; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963.; Leopold, Nathan Freudenthal, 1904-1971.; Sussman, Alfred S.; Goldenberg, Edie N.
- Dean’s Files 1916-2008
  The Dean's Files series constitutes the central file of the office covering the years 1916-2008. The organization and substantive content of the Dean's files changed over the years. In the early period a single alphabetical file covered a span of years. Later there is a separate alphabetical file for each academic year. The annual alphabetical files were later subdivided into an alphabetical Topical File and files for Departments, Centers/Programs, Museums, Laboratories/Gardens, Institutes, and Committees. The content of the Dean's files evolved over the years form being primarily routine correspondence to the central administrative record of the college. The records were received in several accession. In this finding aid, the dean's files from the various accessions have been brought together. As a result the box numbers are not always consecutive.